Guide to the William Jay Foltz African Political Ephemera Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Jay Foltz African political ephemera collection
1952-1999
MS 2001
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(6 boxes)
The collection consists of various documents collected by William Jay Foltz from the 1960s through the 1990s relating to political developments and conflicts in Senegal, Mali, Ghana, Chad, Nigeria, Uganda, Southern Rhodesia, Kenya and South Africa.
Biographical / Historical
William Jay Foltz was Professor Emeritus of African Studies and Political Science at Yale University from 1963 until 2013. He was born in Mount Vernon, New York, in 1936 and received his A.B. at Princeton in 1957 and his Ph.D. from Yale in 1963. He was the first director of the Yale Center for International and Area Studies (now the Macmillan Center) from 1983 to 1989 where he greatly expanded faculty and university programs in international relations. He served as Chair of the Council on African Studies, Chair of the Political Science Department and was Associate Director of Yale's Southern African Research Program for 15 years. He was a consultant to the Rand Corporation and the U.S. Department of State. In addition, he was a Senior Fellow at the Council on Foreign Relations and served on the National Intelligence Council as the National Intelligence Officer for Africa from 1995 to 1997. Professor Foltz died in New Haven, Connecticut in October 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator, 2014.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of various documents collected by William Jay Foltz from the 1960s through the 1990s relating to political developments and conflicts in Senegal, Mali, Ghana, Chad, Nigeria, Uganda, Southern Rhodesia, Kenya and South Africa.
Africa -- Politics and government; Chad -- Politics and government; Kenya -- Politics and government; Mali -- Politics and government; Nigeria -- Politics and government; Senegal -- Politics and government; South Africa -- Politics and government; Uganda -- Politics and government; Senghor, Léopold Sédar, 1906-2001; Organization of African Unity
- Assessing Vulnerability to Ethnic Conflict, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Baako, Kofi, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Chad, debates
  General
  Material on microfilm.
  - 1952 (Reel 3)
  - 1957-1958 (Reel 4)
- Kaduma, Ndugu I. M., 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Keita, Modibo, speech, 1964 November 28; 1 (Box 5)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
- The Killing of Kenyatta's Critic, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Nigeria material, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Organization of African Unity (O.A.U.), notes and documents on western Sahara, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- L'OUA et le Nouvel Ordre Juridique International, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Parti Africain de l'indépendance, Senegal, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
- Senghor, Leopold, interview, 1964 July 10; 1 (Box 6)
- Southern Rhodesia negotiations, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous, 1972-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)